<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.1//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11/DTD/xhtml11.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en">
   <head>
      <title>Bhagavad Gita AS IT IS</title>
      <link rel="stylesheet" href="book.css" type="text/css"/>
      <meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="application/xhtml+xml; charset=utf-8"/>
   </head>
      <body>
<h1>CHAPTER 1</h1>
<h2>Seeing the Armies on the Battlefield of Kurukñetra</h2>
<h3>Bg 1.1</h3>
<h4>TEXT 1</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Da*Taraí&#92; ovac</p>
<p>DaMaR+ae}ae ku-å+ae}ae SaMaveTaa YauYauTSav&#34; )</p>
<p>MaaMak-a&#34; Paa&#60;@vaêEv ik-Maku-vRTa SaÅYa )) 1 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>dhåtaräñöra uväca</p>
<p>dharma-kñetre kuru-kñetre</p>
<p>samavetä yuyutsavaù</p>
<p>mämakäù päëòaväç caiva</p>
<p>kim akurvata saïjaya</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">dhåtaräñöraù uväca—King Dhåtaräñöra said; dharma-kñetre—in the place of pilgrimage; kuru-kñetre—in the place named Kurukñetra; samavetäù—assembled; yuyutsavaù—desiring to fight; mämakäù—my party (sons); päëòaväù—the sons of Päëòu; ca—and; eva—certainly; kim—what; akurvata—did they do; saïjaya—O Saïjaya.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Dhåtaräñöra said: O Saïjaya, after my sons and the sons of Päëòu assembled in the place of pilgrimage at Kurukñetra, desiring to fight, what did they do?</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Bhagavad-gétä is the widely read theistic science summarized in the Gétä-mähätmya (Glorification of the Gétä). There it says that one should read Bhagavad-gétä very scrutinizingly with the help of a person who is a devotee of Çré Kåñëa and try to understand it without personally motivated interpretations. The example of clear understanding is there in the Bhagavad-gétä itself, in the way the teaching is understood by Arjuna, who heard the Gétä directly from the Lord. If someone is fortunate enough to understand Bhagavad-gétä in that line of disciplic succession, without motivated interpretation, then he surpasses all studies of Vedic wisdom, and all scriptures of the world. One will find in the Bhagavad-gétä all that is contained in other scriptures, but the reader will also find things which are not to be found elsewhere. That is the specific standard of the Gétä. It is the perfect theistic science because it is directly spoken by the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Lord Çré Kåñëa.</p>
<p>The topics discussed by Dhåtaräñöra and Saïjaya, as described in the Mahäbhärata, form the basic principle for this great philosophy. It is understood that this philosophy evolved on the Battlefield of Kurukñetra, which is a sacred place of pilgrimage from the immemorial time of the Vedic age. It was spoken by the Lord when He was present personally on this planet for the guidance of mankind.</p>
<p>The word dharma-kñetra (a place where religious rituals are performed) is significant because, on the Battlefield of Kurukñetra, the Supreme Personality of Godhead was present on the side of Arjuna. Dhåtaräñöra, the father of the Kurus, was highly doubtful about the possibility of his sons’ ultimate victory. In his doubt, he inquired from his secretary Saïjaya, “What did they do?” He was confident that both his sons and the sons of his younger brother Päëòu were assembled in that Field of Kurukñetra for a determined engagement of the war. Still, his inquiry is significant. He did not want a compromise between the cousins and brothers, and he wanted to be sure of the fate of his sons on the battlefield. Because the battle was arranged to be fought at Kurukñetra, which is mentioned elsewhere in the Vedas as a place of worship—even for the denizens of heaven—Dhåtaräñöra became very fearful about the influence of the holy place on the outcome of the battle. He knew very well that this would influence Arjuna and the sons of Päëòu favorably, because by nature they were all virtuous. Saïjaya was a student of Vyäsa, and therefore, by the mercy of Vyäsa, Saïjaya was able to envision the Battlefield of Kurukñetra even while he was in the room of Dhåtaräñöra. And so, Dhåtaräñöra asked him about the situation on the battlefield.</p>
<p>Both the Päëòavas and the sons of Dhåtaräñöra belong to the same family, but Dhåtaräñöra’s mind is disclosed herein. He deliberately claimed only his sons as Kurus, and he separated the sons of Päëòu from the family heritage. One can thus understand the specific position of Dhåtaräñöra in his relationship with his nephews, the sons of Päëòu. As in the paddy field the unnecessary plants are taken out, so it is expected from the very beginning of these topics that in the religious field of Kurukñetra, where the father of religion, Çré Kåñëa, was present, the unwanted plants like Dhåtaräñöra’s son Duryodhana and others would be wiped out and the thoroughly religious persons, headed by Yudhiñöhira, would be established by the Lord. This is the significance of the words dharma-kñetre and kuru-kñetre, apart from their historical and Vedic importance.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.2</h3>
<h4>TEXT 2</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>SaÅYa ovac</p>
<p>d*îa Tau Paa&#60;@vaNaqk&#38;- VYaU!&#38; duYaaeRDaNaSTada )</p>
<p>AacaYaRMauPaSa®MYa raJaa vcNaMab]vqTa( )) 2 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>saïjaya uväca</p>
<p>dåñövä tu päëòavänékaà</p>
<p>vyüòhaà duryodhanas tadä</p>
<p>äcäryam upasaìgamya</p>
<p>räjä vacanam abravét</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">saïjayaù uväca—Saïjaya said; dåñövä—after seeing; tu—but; päëòava-anékam—the soldiers of the Päëòavas; vyüòham—arranged in a military phalanx; duryodhanaù—King Duryodhana; tadä—at that time; äcäryam—the teacher; upasaìgamya—approaching; räjä—the king; vacanam—words; abravét—spoke.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Saïjaya said: O King, after looking over the army arranged in military formation by the sons of Päëòu, King Duryodhana went to his teacher and spoke the following words.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Dhåtaräñöra was blind from birth. Unfortunately, he was also bereft of spiritual vision. He knew very well that his sons were equally blind in the matter of religion, and he was sure that they could never reach an understanding with the Päëòavas, who were all pious since birth. Still he was doubtful about the influence of the place of pilgrimage, and Saïjaya could understand his motive in asking about the situation on the battlefield. Saïjaya wanted, therefore, to encourage the despondent king and thus assured him that his sons were not going to make any sort of compromise under the influence of the holy place. Saïjaya therefore informed the king that his son, Duryodhana, after seeing the military force of the Päëòavas, at once went to the commander in chief, Droëäcärya, to inform him of the real position. Although Duryodhana is mentioned as the king, he still had to go to the commander on account of the seriousness of the situation. He was therefore quite fit to be a politician. But Duryodhana’s diplomatic veneer could not disguise the fear he felt when he saw the military arrangement of the Päëòavas.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.3</h3>
<h4>TEXT 3</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>PaXYaETaa&#38; Paa&#60;@uPau}aa&#60;aaMaacaYaR MahTaq&#38; cMaUMa( )</p>
<p>VYaU!a&#38; d]uPadPau}ae&#60;a Tav iXaZYae&#60;a DaqMaTaa )) 3 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>paçyaitäà päëòu-puträëäm</p>
<p>äcärya mahatéà camüm</p>
<p>vyüòhäà drupada-putreëa</p>
<p>tava çiñyeëa dhématä</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">paçya—behold; etäm—this; päëòu-puträëäm—of the sons of Päëòu; äcärya—O teacher; mahatém—great; camüm—military force; vyüòhäm—arranged; drupada-putreëa—by the son of Drupada; tava—your; çiñyeëa—disciple; dhé-matä—very intelligent.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">O my teacher, behold the great army of the sons of Päëòu, so expertly arranged by your intelligent disciple the son of Drupada.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Duryodhana, a great diplomat, wanted to point out the defects of Droëäcärya, the great brähmaëa commander in chief. Droëäcärya had some political quarrel with King Drupada, the father of Draupadé, who was Arjuna’s wife. As a result of this quarrel, Drupada performed a great sacrifice, by which he received the benediction of having a son who would be able to kill Droëäcärya. Droëäcärya knew this perfectly well, and yet as a liberal brähmaëa he did not hesitate to impart all his military secrets when the son of Drupada, Dhåñöadyumna, was entrusted to him for military education. Now, on the Battlefield of Kurukñetra, Dhåñöadyumna took the side of the Päëòavas, and it was he who arranged for their military phalanx, after having learned the art from Droëäcärya. Duryodhana pointed out this mistake of Droëäcärya’s so that he might be alert and uncompromising in the fighting. By this he wanted to point out also that he should not be similarly lenient in battle against the Päëòavas, who were also Droëäcärya’s affectionate students. Arjuna, especially, was his most affectionate and brilliant student. Duryodhana also warned that such leniency in the fight would lead to defeat.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.4</h3>
<h4>TEXT 4</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>A}a éUra MaheZvaSaa &#62;aqMaaJauRNaSaMaa YauiDa )</p>
<p>YauYauDaaNaae ivra$=ê d]uPadê MaharQa&#34; )) 4 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>atra çürä maheñv-äsä</p>
<p>bhémärjuna-samä yudhi</p>
<p>yuyudhäno viräöaç ca</p>
<p>drupadaç ca mahä-rathaù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">atra—here; çüräù—heroes; mahä-iñu-äsäù—mighty bowmen; bhéma-arjuna—to Bhéma and Arjuna; samäù—equal; yudhi—in the fight; yuyudhänaù—Yuyudhäna; viräöaù—Viräöa; ca—also; drupadaù—Drupada; ca—also; mahä-rathaù—great fighter.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Here in this army are many heroic bowmen equal in fighting to Bhéma and Arjuna: great fighters like Yuyudhäna, Viräöa and Drupada.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Even though Dhåñöadyumna was not a very important obstacle in the face of Droëäcärya’s very great power in the military art, there were many others who were causes of fear. They are mentioned by Duryodhana as great stumbling blocks on the path of victory because each and every one of them was as formidable as Bhéma and Arjuna. He knew the strength of Bhéma and Arjuna, and thus he compared the others with them.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.5</h3>
<h4>TEXT 5</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Da*íke-Tauêeik-TaaNa&#34; k-aiXaraJaê vqYaRvaNa( )</p>
<p>PauåiJaTku-iNTa&#62;aaeJaê XaEBYaê NarPau®v&#34; )) 5 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>dhåñöaketuç cekitänaù</p>
<p>käçiräjaç ca véryavän</p>
<p>purujit kuntibhojaç ca</p>
<p>çaibyaç ca nara-puìgavaù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">dhåñöaketuù—Dhåñöaketu; cekitänaù—Cekitäna; käçiräjaù—Käçiräja; ca—also; vérya-vän—very powerful; purujit—Purujit; kuntibhojaù—Kuntibhoja; ca—and; çaibyaù—Çaibya; ca—and; nara-puìgavaù—hero in human society.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">There are also great, heroic, powerful fighters like Dhåñöaketu, Cekitäna, Käçiräja, Purujit, Kuntibhoja and Çaibya.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.6</h3>
<h4>TEXT 6</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>YauDaaMaNYauê iv§-aNTa otaMaaEJaaê vqYaRvaNa( )</p>
<p>SaaE&#62;ad]ae d]aEPadeYaaê SavR Wv MaharQaa&#34; )) 6 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>yudhämanyuç ca vikränta</p>
<p>uttamaujäç ca véryavän</p>
<p>saubhadro draupadeyäç ca</p>
<p>sarva eva mahä-rathäù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">yudhämanyuù—Yudhämanyu; ca—and; vikräntaù—mighty; uttamaujäù—Uttamaujä; ca—and; vérya-vän—very powerful; saubhadraù—the son of Subhadrä; draupadeyäù—the sons of Draupadé; ca—and; sarve—all; eva—certainly; mahä-rathäù—great chariot fighters.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">There are the mighty Yudhämanyu, the very powerful Uttamaujä, the son of Subhadrä and the sons of Draupadé. All these warriors are great chariot fighters.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.7</h3>
<h4>TEXT 7</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>ASMaak&#38;- Tau iviXaía Yae TaaiàbaeDa iÜJaaetaMa )</p>
<p>NaaYak-a MaMa SaENYaSYa Sa&#38;jaQa| TaaNb]vqiMa Tae )) 7 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>asmäkaà tu viçiñöä ye</p>
<p>tän nibodha dvijottama</p>
<p>näyakä mama sainyasya</p>
<p>saàjïärthaà tän bravémi te</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">asmäkam—our; tu—but; viçiñöäù—especially powerful; ye—who; tän—them; nibodha—just take note of, be informed; dvija-uttama—O best of the brähmaëas; näyakäù—captains; mama—my; sainyasya—of the soldiers; saàjïä-artham—for information; tän—them; bravémi—I am speaking; te—to you.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">But for your information, O best of the brähmaëas, let me tell you about the captains who are especially qualified to lead my military force.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.8</h3>
<h4>TEXT 8</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>&#62;avaN&#62;aqZMaê k-&#60;aRê k*-Paê SaiMaiTa&#38;JaYa&#34; )</p>
<p>AìTQaaMaa ivk-&#60;aRê SaaEMaditaSTaQaEv c )) 8 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>bhavän bhéñmaç ca karëaç ca</p>
<p>kåpaç ca samitià-jayaù</p>
<p>açvatthämä vikarëaç ca</p>
<p>saumadattis tathaiva ca</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">bhavän—your good self; bhéñmaù—Grandfather Bhéñma; ca—also; karëaù—Karëa; ca—and; kåpaù—Kåpa; ca—and; samitim-jayaù—always victorious in battle; açvatthämä—Açvatthämä; vikarëaù—Vikarëa; ca—as well as; saumadattiù—the son of Somadatta; tathä—as well as; eva—certainly; ca—also.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">There are personalities like you, Bhéñma, Karëa, Kåpa, Açvatthämä, Vikarëa and the son of Somadatta called Bhüriçravä, who are always victorious in battle.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Duryodhana mentions the exceptional heroes in the battle, all of whom are ever victorious. Vikarëa is the brother of Duryodhana, Açvatthämä is the son of Droëäcärya, and Saumadatti, or Bhüriçravä, is the son of the King of the Bählékas. Karëa is the half brother of Arjuna, as he was born of Kunté before her marriage with King Päëòu. Kåpäcärya’s twin sister married Droëäcärya.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.9</h3>
<h4>TEXT 9</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>ANYae c bhv&#34; éUra MadQaeR TYa¢-JaqivTaa&#34; )</p>
<p>NaaNaaXañPa[hr&#60;aa&#34; SaveR YauÖivXaarda&#34; )) 9 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>anye ca bahavaù çürä</p>
<p>mad-arthe tyakta-jévitäù</p>
<p>nänä-çastra-praharaëäù</p>
<p>sarve yuddha-viçäradäù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">anye—others; ca—also; bahavaù—in great numbers; çüräù—heroes; mat-arthe—for my sake; tyakta-jévitäù—prepared to risk life; nänä—many; çastra—weapons; praharaëäù—equipped with; sarve—all of them; yuddha-viçäradäù—experienced in military science.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">There are many other heroes who are prepared to lay down their lives for my sake. All of them are well equipped with different kinds of weapons, and all are experienced in military science.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">As far as the others are concerned—like Jayadratha, Kåtavarmä and Çalya—all are determined to lay down their lives for Duryodhana’s sake. In other words, it is already concluded that all of them would die in the Battle of Kurukñetra for joining the party of the sinful Duryodhana. Duryodhana was, of course, confident of his victory on account of the above-mentioned combined strength of his friends.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.10</h3>
<h4>TEXT 10</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>APaYaaRá&#38; TadSMaak&#38;- bl&#38;&#47; &#62;aqZMaai&#62;ari+aTaMa( )</p>
<p>PaYaaRá&#38; iTvdMaeTaeza&#38; bl&#38;&#47; &#62;aqMaai&#62;ari+aTaMa( )) 10 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>aparyäptaà tad asmäkaà</p>
<p>balaà bhéñmäbhirakñitam</p>
<p>paryäptaà tv idam eteñäà</p>
<p>balaà bhémäbhirakñitam</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">aparyäptam—immeasurable; tat—that; asmäkam—of ours; balam—strength; bhéñma—by Grandfather Bhéñma; abhirakñitam—perfectly protected; paryäptam—limited; tu—but; idam—all this; eteñäm—of the Päëòavas; balam—strength; bhéma—by Bhéma; abhirakñitam—carefully protected.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Our strength is immeasurable, and we are perfectly protected by Grandfather Bhéñma, whereas the strength of the Päëòavas, carefully protected by Bhéma, is limited.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Herein an estimation of comparative strength is made by Duryodhana. He thinks that the strength of his armed forces is immeasurable, being specifically protected by the most experienced general, Grandfather Bhéñma. On the other hand, the forces of the Päëòavas are limited, being protected by a less experienced general, Bhéma, who is like a fig in the presence of Bhéñma. Duryodhana was always envious of Bhéma because he knew perfectly well that if he should die at all, he would only be killed by Bhéma. But at the same time, he was confident of his victory on account of the presence of Bhéñma, who was a far superior general. His conclusion that he would come out of the battle victorious was well ascertained.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.11</h3>
<h4>TEXT 11</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>AYaNaezu c SaveRzu YaQaa&#62;aaGaMaviSQaTaa&#34; )</p>
<p>&#62;aqZMaMaevai&#62;ar+aNTau &#62;avNTa&#34; SavR Wv ih )) 11 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>ayaneñu ca sarveñu</p>
<p>yathä-bhägam avasthitäù</p>
<p>bhéñmam eväbhirakñantu</p>
<p>bhavantaù sarva eva hi</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">ayaneñu—in the strategic points; ca—also; sarveñu—everywhere; yathä-bhägam—as differently arranged; avasthitäù—situated; bhéñmam—unto Grandfather Bhéñma; eva—certainly; abhirakñantu—should give support; bhavantaù—you; sarve—all respectively; eva hi—certainly.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">All of you must now give full support to Grandfather Bhéñma, as you stand at your respective strategic points of entrance into the phalanx of the army.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Duryodhana, after praising the prowess of Bhéñma, further considered that others might think that they had been considered less important, so in his usual diplomatic way, he tried to adjust the situation in the above words. He emphasized that Bhéñmadeva was undoubtedly the greatest hero, but he was an old man, so everyone must especially think of his protection from all sides. He might become engaged in the fight, and the enemy might take advantage of his full engagement on one side. Therefore, it was important that other heroes not leave their strategic positions and allow the enemy to break the phalanx. Duryodhana clearly felt that the victory of the Kurus depended on the presence of Bhéñmadeva. He was confident of the full support of Bhéñmadeva and Droëäcärya in the battle because he well knew that they did not even speak a word when Arjuna’s wife Draupadé, in her helpless condition, had appealed to them for justice while she was being forced to appear naked in the presence of all the great generals in the assembly. Although he knew that the two generals had some sort of affection for the Päëòavas, he hoped that these generals would now completely give it up, as they had done during the gambling performances.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.12</h3>
<h4>TEXT 12</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>TaSYa SaÅNaYaNhz| ku-åv*Ö&#34; iPaTaaMah&#34; )</p>
<p>iSa&#38;hNaad&#38; ivNaÛaeÀE&#34; Xa«&#38; dDMaaE Pa[TaaPavaNa( )) 12 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>tasya saïjanayan harñaà</p>
<p>kuru-våddhaù pitämahaù</p>
<p>siàha-nädaà vinadyoccaiù</p>
<p>çaìkhaà dadhmau pratäpavän</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">tasya—his; saïjanayan—increasing; harñam—cheerfulness; kuru-våddhaù—the grandsire of the Kuru dynasty (Bhéñma); pitämahaù—the grandfather; siàha-nädam—roaring sound, like that of a lion; vinadya—vibrating; uccaiù—very loudly; çaìkham—conchshell; dadhmau—blew; pratäpa-vän—the valiant.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Then Bhéñma, the great valiant grandsire of the Kuru dynasty, the grandfather of the fighters, blew his conchshell very loudly, making a sound like the roar of a lion, giving Duryodhana joy.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">The grandsire of the Kuru dynasty could understand the inner meaning of the heart of his grandson Duryodhana, and out of his natural compassion for him he tried to cheer him by blowing his conchshell very loudly, befitting his position as a lion. Indirectly, by the symbolism of the conchshell, he informed his depressed grandson Duryodhana that he had no chance of victory in the battle, because the Supreme Lord Kåñëa was on the other side. But still, it was his duty to conduct the fight, and no pains would be spared in that connection.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.13</h3>
<h4>TEXT 13</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>TaTa&#34; Xa«aê &#62;aeYaRê Pa&#60;avaNak-GaaeMau%a&#34; )</p>
<p>SahSaEva&#62;YahNYaNTa Sa XaBdSTauMaul&#47;ae_&#62;avTa( )) 13 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>tataù çaìkhäç ca bheryaç ca</p>
<p>paëavänaka-gomukhäù</p>
<p>sahasaiväbhyahanyanta</p>
<p>sa çabdas tumulo ’bhavat</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">tataù—thereafter; çaìkhäù—conchshells; ca—also; bheryaù—large drums; ca—and; paëava-änaka—small drums and kettledrums; go-mukhäù—horns; sahasä—all of a sudden; eva—certainly; abhyahanyanta—were simultaneously sounded; saù—that; çabdaù—combined sound; tumulaù—tumultuous; abhavat—became.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">After that, the conchshells, drums, bugles, trumpets and horns were all suddenly sounded, and the combined sound was tumultuous.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.14</h3>
<h4>TEXT 14</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>TaTa&#34; ìeTaEhRYaEYauR¢e- MahiTa SYaNdNae iSQaTaaE )</p>
<p>MaaDav&#34; Paa&#60;@vêEv idVYaaE Xa«aE Pa[dDMaTau&#34; )) 14 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>tataù çvetair hayair yukte</p>
<p>mahati syandane sthitau</p>
<p>mädhavaù päëòavaç caiva</p>
<p>divyau çaìkhau pradadhmatuù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">tataù—thereafter; çvetaiù—with white; hayaiù—horses; yukte—being yoked; mahati—in a great; syandane—chariot; sthitau—situated; mädhavaù—Kåñëa (the husband of the goddess of fortune); päëòavaù—Arjuna (the son of Päëòu); ca—also; eva—certainly; divyau—transcendental; çaìkhau—conchshells; pradadhmatuù—sounded.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">On the other side, both Lord Kåñëa and Arjuna, stationed on a great chariot drawn by white horses, sounded their transcendental conchshells.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">In contrast with the conchshell blown by Bhéñmadeva, the conchshells in the hands of Kåñëa and Arjuna are described as transcendental. The sounding of the transcendental conchshells indicated that there was no hope of victory for the other side because Kåñëa was on the side of the Päëòavas. Jayas tu päëòu-puträëäà yeñäà pakñe janärdanaù. Victory is always with persons like the sons of Päëòu because Lord Kåñëa is associated with them. And whenever and wherever the Lord is present, the goddess of fortune is also there because the goddess of fortune never lives alone without her husband. Therefore, victory and fortune were awaiting Arjuna, as indicated by the transcendental sound produced by the conchshell of Viñëu, or Lord Kåñëa. Besides that, the chariot on which both the friends were seated had been donated by Agni (the fire-god) to Arjuna, and this indicated that this chariot was capable of conquering all sides, wherever it was drawn over the three worlds.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.15</h3>
<h4>TEXT 15</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>PaaÄJaNYa&#38; ôzqke-Xaae devdta&#38; DaNaÅYa&#34; )</p>
<p>PaaE&#60;@&#92;&#38; dDMaaE MahaXa«&#38; &#62;aqMak-MaaR v*k-aedr&#34; )) 15 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>päïcajanyaà håñékeço</p>
<p>devadattaà dhanaïjayaù</p>
<p>pauëòraà dadhmau mahä-çaìkhaà</p>
<p>bhéma-karmä våkodaraù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">päïcajanyam—the conchshell named Päïcajanya; håñéka-éçaù—Håñékeça (Kåñëa, the Lord who directs the senses of the devotees); devadattam—the conchshell named Devadatta; dhanam-jayaù—Dhanaïjaya (Arjuna, the winner of wealth); pauëòram—the conch named Pauëòra; dadhmau—blew; mahä-çaìkham—the terrific conchshell; bhéma-karmä—one who performs herculean tasks; våka-udaraù—the voracious eater (Bhéma).</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Lord Kåñëa blew His conchshell, called Päïcajanya; Arjuna blew his, the Devadatta; and Bhéma, the voracious eater and performer of herculean tasks, blew his terrific conchshell, called Pauëòra.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Lord Kåñëa is referred to as Håñékeça in this verse because He is the owner of all senses. The living entities are part and parcel of Him, and therefore the senses of the living entities are also part and parcel of His senses. The impersonalists cannot account for the senses of the living entities, and therefore they are always anxious to describe all living entities as senseless, or impersonal. The Lord, situated in the hearts of all living entities, directs their senses. But He directs in terms of the surrender of the living entity, and in the case of a pure devotee He directly controls the senses. Here on the Battlefield of Kurukñetra the Lord directly controls the transcendental senses of Arjuna, and thus His particular name of Håñékeça. The Lord has different names according to His different activities. For example, His name is Madhusüdana because He killed the demon of the name Madhu; His name is Govinda because He gives pleasure to the cows and to the senses; His name is Väsudeva because He appeared as the son of Vasudeva; His name is Devaké-nandana because He accepted Devaké as His mother; His name is Yaçodä-nandana because He awarded His childhood pastimes to Yaçodä at Våndävana; His name is Pärtha-särathi because He worked as charioteer of His friend Arjuna. Similarly, His name is Håñékeça because He gave direction to Arjuna on the Battlefield of Kurukñetra.</p>
<p>Arjuna is referred to as Dhanaïjaya in this verse because he helped his elder brother in fetching wealth when it was required by the king to make expenditures for different sacrifices. Similarly, Bhéma is known as Våkodara because he could eat as voraciously as he could perform herculean tasks, such as killing the demon Hiòimba. So the particular types of conchshell blown by the different personalities on the side of the Päëòavas, beginning with the Lord’s, were all very encouraging to the fighting soldiers. On the other side there were no such credits, nor the presence of Lord Kåñëa, the supreme director, nor that of the goddess of fortune. So they were predestined to lose the battle—and that was the message announced by the sounds of the conchshells.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.16, Bg 1.17, Bg 1.18, Bg 1.16-18</h3>
<h4>TEXTS 16–18</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>ANaNTaivJaYa&#38; raJaa ku-NTaqPau}aae YauiDaiïr&#34; )</p>
<p>Naku-l&#47;&#34; Sahdevê SaugaaezMai&#60;aPauZPak-aE )) 16 ))</p>
<br />
<p>k-aXYaê ParMaeZvaSa&#34; iXa%&#60;@q c MaharQa&#34; )</p>
<p>Da*íÛuManae ivra$=ê SaaTYaik-êaParaiJaTa&#34; )) 17 ))</p>
<br />
<p>d]uPadae d]aEPadeYaaê SavRXa&#34; Pa*iQavqPaTae )</p>
<p>SaaE&#62;ad]ê Mahabahu&#34; Xa«aNdDMau&#34; Pa*QaKPa*Qak(- )) 18 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>anantavijayaà räjä</p>
<p>kunté-putro yudhiñöhiraù</p>
<p>nakulaù sahadevaç ca</p>
<p>sughoña-maëipuñpakau</p>
<br />
<p>käçyaç ca parameñv-äsaù</p>
<p>çikhaëòé ca mahä-rathaù</p>
<p>dhåñöadyumno viräöaç ca</p>
<p>sätyakiç cäparäjitaù</p>
<br />
<p>drupado draupadeyäç ca</p>
<p>sarvaçaù påthivé-pate</p>
<p>saubhadraç ca mahä-bähuù</p>
<p>çaìkhän dadhmuù påthak påthak</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">ananta-vijayam—the conch named Ananta-vijaya; räjä—the king; kunté-putraù—the son of Kunté; yudhiñöhiraù—Yudhiñöhira; nakulaù—Nakula; sahadevaù—Sahadeva; ca—and; sughoña-maëipuñpakau—the conches named Sughoña and Maëipuñpaka; käçyaù—the King of Käçé (Väräëasé); ca—and; parama-iñu-äsaù—the great archer; çikhaëòé—Çikhaëòé; ca—also; mahä-rathaù—one who can fight alone against thousands; dhåñöadyumnaù—Dhåñöadyumna (the son of King Drupada); viräöaù—Viräöa (the prince who gave shelter to the Päëòavas while they were in disguise); ca—also; sätyakiù—Sätyaki (the same as Yuyudhäna, the charioteer of Lord Kåñëa); ca—and; aparäjitaù—who had never been vanquished; drupadaù—Drupada, the King of Päïcäla; draupadeyäù—the sons of Draupadé; ca—also; sarvaçaù—all; påthivé-pate—O King; saubhadraù—Abhimanyu, the son of Subhadrä; ca—also; mahä-bähuù—mighty-armed; çaìkhän—conchshells; dadhmuù—blew; påthak påthak—each separately.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">King Yudhiñöhira, the son of Kunté, blew his conchshell, the Ananta-vijaya, and Nakula and Sahadeva blew the Sughoña and Maëipuñpaka. That great archer the King of Käçé, the great fighter Çikhaëòé, Dhåñöadyumna, Viräöa, the unconquerable Sätyaki, Drupada, the sons of Draupadé, and the others, O King, such as the mighty-armed son of Subhadrä, all blew their respective conchshells.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Saïjaya informed King Dhåtaräñöra very tactfully that his unwise policy of deceiving the sons of Päëòu and endeavoring to enthrone his own sons on the seat of the kingdom was not very laudable. The signs already clearly indicated that the whole Kuru dynasty would be killed in that great battle. Beginning with the grandsire, Bhéñma, down to the grandsons like Abhimanyu and others—including kings from many states of the world—all were present there, and all were doomed. The whole catastrophe was due to King Dhåtaräñöra, because he encouraged the policy followed by his sons.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.19</h3>
<h4>TEXT 19</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Sa gaaezae DaaTaRraí&#92;a&#60;aa&#38; ôdYaaiNa VYadarYaTa( )</p>
<p>Na&#62;aê Pa*iQavq&#38; cEv TauMaul&#47;ae_&#62;YaNauNaadYaNa( )) 19 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>sa ghoño dhärtaräñöräëäà</p>
<p>hådayäni vyadärayat</p>
<p>nabhaç ca påthivéà caiva</p>
<p>tumulo ’bhyanunädayan</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">saù—that; ghoñaù—vibration; dhärtaräñöräëäm—of the sons of Dhåtaräñöra; hådayäni—hearts; vyadärayat—shattered; nabhaù—the sky; ca—also; påthivém—the surface of the earth; ca—also; eva—certainly; tumulaù—uproarious; abhyanunädayan—resounding.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">The blowing of these different conchshells became uproarious. Vibrating both in the sky and on the earth, it shattered the hearts of the sons of Dhåtaräñöra.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">When Bhéñma and the others on the side of Duryodhana blew their respective conchshells, there was no heart-breaking on the part of the Päëòavas. Such occurrences are not mentioned, but in this particular verse it is mentioned that the hearts of the sons of Dhåtaräñöra were shattered by the sounds vibrated by the Päëòavas’ party. This is due to the Päëòavas and their confidence in Lord Kåñëa. One who takes shelter of the Supreme Lord has nothing to fear, even in the midst of the greatest calamity.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.20</h3>
<h4>TEXT 20</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>AQa VYaviSQaTaaNd*îa DaaTaRraí&#92;aNk-iPaßJa&#34; )</p>
<p>Pa[v*tae XañSaMPaaTae DaNauåÛMYa Paa&#60;@v&#34; )</p>
<p>ôzqke-Xa&#38; Tada vaKYaiMadMaah MahqPaTae )) 20 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>atha vyavasthitän dåñövä</p>
<p>dhärtaräñörän kapi-dhvajaù</p>
<p>pravåtte çastra-sampäte</p>
<p>dhanur udyamya päëòavaù</p>
<p>håñékeçaà tadä väkyam</p>
<p>idam äha mahé-pate</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">atha—thereupon; vyavasthitän—situated; dåñövä—looking upon; dhärtaräñörän—the sons of Dhåtaräñöra; kapi-dhvajaù—he whose flag was marked with Hanumän; pravåtte—while about to engage; çastra-sampäte—in releasing his arrows; dhanuù—bow; udyamya—taking up; päëòavaù—the son of Päëòu (Arjuna); håñékeçam—unto Lord Kåñëa; tadä—at that time; väkyam—words; idam—these; äha—said; mahé-pate—O King.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">At that time Arjuna, the son of Päëòu, seated in the chariot bearing the flag marked with Hanumän, took up his bow and prepared to shoot his arrows. O King, after looking at the sons of Dhåtaräñöra drawn in military array, Arjuna then spoke to Lord Kåñëa these words.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">The battle was just about to begin. It is understood from the above statement that the sons of Dhåtaräñöra were more or less disheartened by the unexpected arrangement of military force by the Päëòavas, who were guided by the direct instructions of Lord Kåñëa on the battlefield. The emblem of Hanumän on the flag of Arjuna is another sign of victory because Hanumän cooperated with Lord Räma in the battle between Räma and Rävaëa, and Lord Räma emerged victorious. Now both Räma and Hanumän were present on the chariot of Arjuna to help him. Lord Kåñëa is Räma Himself, and wherever Lord Räma is, His eternal servitor Hanumän and His eternal consort Sétä, the goddess of fortune, are present. Therefore, Arjuna had no cause to fear any enemies whatsoever. And above all, the Lord of the senses, Lord Kåñëa, was personally present to give him direction. Thus, all good counsel was available to Arjuna in the matter of executing the battle. In such auspicious conditions, arranged by the Lord for His eternal devotee, lay the signs of assured victory.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.21, Bg 1.22, Bg 1.21-22</h3>
<h4>TEXTS 21–22</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>AJauRNa ovac</p>
<p>SaeNaYaaeå&#62;aYaaeMaRDYae rQa&#38; SQaaPaYa Mae_CYauTa )</p>
<p>YaavdeTaaiàrq+ae_h&#38; Yaaed(Dauk-aMaaNaviSQaTaaNa( )) 21 ))</p>
<p>kE-MaRYaa Sah YaaeÖVYaMaiSMaNr&#60;aSaMauÛMae )) 22 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>arjuna uväca</p>
<p>senayor ubhayor madhye</p>
<p>rathaà sthäpaya me ’cyuta</p>
<p>yävad etän nirékñe ’haà</p>
<p>yoddhu-kämän avasthitän</p>
<p>kair mayä saha yoddhavyam</p>
<p>asmin raëa-samudyame</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">arjunaù uväca—Arjuna said; senayoù—of the armies; ubhayoù—both; madhye—between; ratham—the chariot; sthäpaya—please keep; me—my; acyuta—O infallible one; yävat—as long as; etän—all these; nirékñe—may look upon; aham—I; yoddhu-kämän—desiring to fight; avasthitän—arrayed on the battlefield; kaiù—with whom; mayä—by me; saha—together; yoddhavyam—have to fight; asmin—in this; raëa—strife; samudyame—in the attempt.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Arjuna said: O infallible one, please draw my chariot between the two armies so that I may see those present here, who desire to fight, and with whom I must contend in this great trial of arms.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Although Lord Kåñëa is the Supreme Personality of Godhead, out of His causeless mercy He was engaged in the service of His friend. He never fails in His affection for His devotees, and thus He is addressed herein as infallible. As charioteer, He had to carry out the orders of Arjuna, and since He did not hesitate to do so, He is addressed as infallible. Although He had accepted the position of a charioteer for His devotee, His supreme position was not challenged. In all circumstances, He is the Supreme Personality of Godhead, Håñékeça, the Lord of the total senses. The relationship between the Lord and His servitor is very sweet and transcendental. The servitor is always ready to render service to the Lord, and, similarly, the Lord is always seeking an opportunity to render some service to the devotee. He takes greater pleasure in His pure devotee’s assuming the advantageous position of ordering Him than He does in being the giver of orders. Since He is master, everyone is under His orders, and no one is above Him to order Him. But when He finds that a pure devotee is ordering Him, He obtains transcendental pleasure, although He is the infallible master of all circumstances.</p>
<p>As a pure devotee of the Lord, Arjuna had no desire to fight with his cousins and brothers, but he was forced to come onto the battlefield by the obstinacy of Duryodhana, who was never agreeable to any peaceful negotiation. Therefore, he was very anxious to see who the leading persons present on the battlefield were. Although there was no question of a peacemaking endeavor on the battlefield, he wanted to see them again, and to see how much they were bent upon demanding an unwanted war.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.23</h3>
<h4>TEXT 23</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>YaaeTSYaMaaNaaNave+ae_h&#38; Ya WTae_}a SaMaaGaTaa&#34; )</p>
<p>DaaTaRraí&#92;SYa dubuRÖeYauRÖe iPa[Yaick-IzRv&#34; )) 23 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>yotsyamänän avekñe ’haà</p>
<p>ya ete ’tra samägatäù</p>
<p>dhärtaräñörasya durbuddher</p>
<p>yuddhe priya-cikérñavaù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">yotsyamänän—those who will be fighting; avekñe—let me see; aham—I; ye—who; ete—those; atra—here; samägatäù—assembled; dhärtaräñörasya—for the son of Dhåtaräñöra; durbuddheù—evil-minded; yuddhe—in the fight; priya—well; cikérñavaù—wishing.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Let me see those who have come here to fight, wishing to please the evil-minded son of Dhåtaräñöra.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">It was an open secret that Duryodhana wanted to usurp the kingdom of the Päëòavas by evil plans, in collaboration with his father, Dhåtaräñöra. Therefore, all persons who had joined the side of Duryodhana must have been birds of the same feather. Arjuna wanted to see them on the battlefield before the fight was begun, just to learn who they were, but he had no intention of proposing peace negotiations with them. It was also a fact that he wanted to see them to make an estimate of the strength which he had to face, although he was quite confident of victory because Kåñëa was sitting by his side.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.24</h3>
<h4>TEXT 24</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>SaÅYa ovac</p>
<p>WvMau¢-ae ôzqke-Xaae Gau@ake-XaeNa &#62;aarTa )</p>
<p>SaeNaYaaeå&#62;aYaaeMaRDYae SQaaPaiYaTva rQaaetaMaMa( )) 24 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>saïjaya uväca</p>
<p>evam ukto håñékeço</p>
<p>guòäkeçena bhärata</p>
<p>senayor ubhayor madhye</p>
<p>sthäpayitvä rathottamam</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">saïjayaù uväca—Saïjaya said; evam—thus; uktaù—addressed; håñékeçaù—Lord Kåñëa; guòäkeçena—by Arjuna; bhärata—O descendant of Bharata; senayoù—of the armies; ubhayoù—both; madhye—in the midst; sthäpayitvä—placing; ratha-uttamam—the finest chariot.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Saïjaya said: O descendant of Bharata, having thus been addressed by Arjuna, Lord Kåñëa drew up the fine chariot in the midst of the armies of both parties.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">In this verse Arjuna is referred to as Guòäkeça. Guòäkä means sleep, and one who conquers sleep is called guòäkeça. Sleep also means ignorance. So Arjuna conquered both sleep and ignorance because of his friendship with Kåñëa. As a great devotee of Kåñëa, he could not forget Kåñëa even for a moment, because that is the nature of a devotee. Either in waking or in sleep, a devotee of the Lord can never be free from thinking of Kåñëa’s name, form, qualities and pastimes. Thus a devotee of Kåñëa can conquer both sleep and ignorance simply by thinking of Kåñëa constantly. This is called Kåñëa consciousness, or samädhi. As Håñékeça, or the director of the senses and mind of every living entity, Kåñëa could understand Arjuna’s purpose in placing the chariot in the midst of the armies. Thus He did so, and spoke as follows.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.25</h3>
<h4>TEXT 25</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>&#62;aqZMad]ae&#60;aPa[Mau%Ta&#34; SaveRza&#38; c Mahqi+aTaaMa( )</p>
<p>ovac PaaQaR PaXYaETaaNSaMaveTaaNku-æiNaiTa )) 25 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>bhéñma-droëa-pramukhataù</p>
<p>sarveñäà ca mahé-kñitäm</p>
<p>uväca pärtha paçyaitän</p>
<p>samavetän kurün iti</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">bhéñma—Grandfather Bhéñma; droëa—the teacher Droëa; pramukhataù—in front of; sarveñäm—all; ca—also; mahé-kñitäm—chiefs of the world; uväca—said; pärtha—O son of Påthä; paçya—just behold; etän—all of them; samavetän—assembled; kurün—the members of the Kuru dynasty; iti—thus.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">In the presence of Bhéñma, Droëa and all the other chieftains of the world, the Lord said, Just behold, Pärtha, all the Kurus assembled here.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">As the Supersoul of all living entities, Lord Kåñëa could understand what was going on in the mind of Arjuna. The use of the word Håñékeça in this connection indicates that He knew everything. And the word Pärtha, or the son of Kunté, or Påthä, is also similarly significant in reference to Arjuna. As a friend, He wanted to inform Arjuna that because Arjuna was the son of Påthä, the sister of His own father Vasudeva, He had agreed to be the charioteer of Arjuna. Now what did Kåñëa mean when He told Arjuna to “behold the Kurus”? Did Arjuna want to stop there and not fight? Kåñëa never expected such things from the son of His aunt Påthä. The mind of Arjuna was thus predicted by the Lord in friendly joking.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.26</h3>
<h4>TEXT 26</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Ta}aaPaXYaiTSQaTaaNPaaQaR&#34; iPaTa›NaQa iPaTaaMahaNa( )</p>
<p>AacaYaaRNMaaTaul&#47;aN&#62;a]aTa›NPau}aaNPaaE}aaNSa%q„&#38;STaQaa )</p>
<p>ìéuraNSauôdêEv SaeNaYaaeå&#62;aYaaeriPa )) 26 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>taträpaçyat sthitän pärthaù</p>
<p>pitèn atha pitämahän</p>
<p>äcäryän mätulän bhrätèn</p>
<p>puträn pauträn sakhéàs tathä</p>
<p>çvaçurän suhådaç caiva</p>
<p>senayor ubhayor api</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">tatra—there; apaçyat—he could see; sthitän—standing; pärthaù—Arjuna; pitèn—fathers; atha—also; pitämahän—grandfathers; äcäryän—teachers; mätulän—maternal uncles; bhrätèn—brothers; puträn—sons; pauträn—grandsons; sakhén—friends; tathä—too; çvaçurän—fathers-in-law; suhådaù—well-wishers; ca—also; eva—certainly; senayoù—of the armies; ubhayoù—of both parties; api—including.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">There Arjuna could see, within the midst of the armies of both parties, his fathers, grandfathers, teachers, maternal uncles, brothers, sons, grandsons, friends, and also his fathers-in-law and well-wishers.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">On the battlefield Arjuna could see all kinds of relatives. He could see persons like Bhüriçravä, who were his father’s contemporaries, grandfathers Bhéñma and Somadatta, teachers like Droëäcärya and Kåpäcärya, maternal uncles like Çalya and Çakuni, brothers like Duryodhana, sons like Lakñmaëa, friends like Açvatthämä, well-wishers like Kåtavarmä, etc. He could see also the armies which contained many of his friends.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.27</h3>
<h4>TEXT 27</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>TaaNSaMaq+Ya Sa k-aENTaeYa&#34; SavaRNbNDaUNaviSQaTaaNa( )</p>
<p>k*-PaYaa ParYaaivíae ivzqdiàdMab]vqTa( )) 27 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>tän samékñya sa kaunteyaù</p>
<p>sarvän bandhün avasthitän</p>
<p>kåpayä parayäviñöo</p>
<p>viñédann idam abravét</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">tän—all of them; samékñya—after seeing; saù—he; kaunteyaù—the son of Kunté; sarvän—all kinds of; bandhün—relatives; avasthitän—situated; kåpayä—by compassion; parayä—of a high grade; äviñöaù—overwhelmed; viñédan—while lamenting; idam—thus; abravét—spoke.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">When the son of Kunté, Arjuna, saw all these different grades of friends and relatives, he became overwhelmed with compassion and spoke thus.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.28</h3>
<h4>TEXT 28</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>AJauRNa ovac</p>
<p>d*îeMa&#38; SvJaNa&#38; k*-Z&#60;a YauYauTSau&#38; SaMauPaiSQaTaMa( )</p>
<p>SaqdiNTa MaMa Gaa}aai&#60;a Mau%&#38; c PairéuZYaiTa )) 28 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>arjuna uväca</p>
<p>dåñövemaà sva-janaà kåñëa</p>
<p>yuyutsuà samupasthitam</p>
<p>sédanti mama gäträëi</p>
<p>mukhaà ca pariçuñyati</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">arjunaù uväca—Arjuna said; dåñövä—after seeing; imam—all these; sva-janam—kinsmen; kåñëa—O Kåñëa; yuyutsum—all in a fighting spirit; samupasthitam—present; sédanti—are quivering; mama—my; gäträëi—limbs of the body; mukham—mouth; ca—also; pariçuñyati—is drying up.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Arjuna said: My dear Kåñëa, seeing my friends and relatives present before me in such a fighting spirit, I feel the limbs of my body quivering and my mouth drying up.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Any man who has genuine devotion to the Lord has all the good qualities which are found in godly persons or in the demigods, whereas the nondevotee, however advanced he may be in material qualifications by education and culture, lacks in godly qualities. As such, Arjuna, just after seeing his kinsmen, friends and relatives on the battlefield, was at once overwhelmed by compassion for them who had so decided to fight amongst themselves. As far as his soldiers were concerned, he was sympathetic from the beginning, but he felt compassion even for the soldiers of the opposite party, foreseeing their imminent death. And while he was so thinking, the limbs of his body began to quiver, and his mouth became dry. He was more or less astonished to see their fighting spirit. Practically the whole community, all blood relatives of Arjuna, had come to fight with him. This overwhelmed a kind devotee like Arjuna. Although it is not mentioned here, still one can easily imagine that not only were Arjuna’s bodily limbs quivering and his mouth drying up, but he was also crying out of compassion. Such symptoms in Arjuna were not due to weakness but to his softheartedness, a characteristic of a pure devotee of the Lord. It is said therefore :</p>
<div class="quotes">
<p>yasyästi bhaktir bhagavaty akiïcanä</p>
<p>sarvair guëais tatra samäsate suräù</p>
<p>haräv abhaktasya kuto mahad-guëä</p>
<p>mano-rathenäsati dhävato bahiù</p></div>
<p>“One who has unflinching devotion for the Personality of Godhead has all the good qualities of the demigods. But one who is not a devotee of the Lord has only material qualifications that are of little value. This is because he is hovering on the mental plane and is certain to be attracted by the glaring material energy.” (Bhäg. 5.18.12)</p>
<h3>Bg 1.29</h3>
<h4>TEXT 29</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>vePaQauê Xarqre Mae raeMahzRê JaaYaTae )</p>
<p>Gaa&#60;@qv&#38; ó&#38;SaTae hSTaatvKcEv PairdùTae )) 29 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>vepathuç ca çarére me</p>
<p>roma-harñaç ca jäyate</p>
<p>gäëòévaà sraàsate hastät</p>
<p>tvak caiva paridahyate</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">vepathuù—trembling of the body; ca—also; çarére—on the body; me—my; roma-harñaù—standing of hair on end; ca—also; jäyate—is taking place; gäëòévam—the bow of Arjuna; sraàsate—is slipping; hastät—from the hand; tvak—skin; ca—also; eva—certainly; paridahyate—is burning.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">My whole body is trembling, my hair is standing on end, my bow Gäëòéva is slipping from my hand, and my skin is burning.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">There are two kinds of trembling of the body, and two kinds of standings of the hair on end. Such phenomena occur either in great spiritual ecstasy or out of great fear under material conditions. There is no fear in transcendental realization. Arjuna’s symptoms in this situation are out of material fear—namely, loss of life. This is evident from other symptoms also; he became so impatient that his famous bow Gäëòéva was slipping from his hands, and, because his heart was burning within him, he was feeling a burning sensation of the skin. All these are due to a material conception of life.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.30</h3>
<h4>TEXT 30</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Na c Xa¥-aeMYavSQaaTau&#38; &#62;a]MaTaqv c Mae MaNa&#34; )</p>
<p>iNaiMataaiNa c PaXYaaiMa ivParqTaaiNa ke-Xav )) 30 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>na ca çaknomy avasthätuà</p>
<p>bhramatéva ca me manaù</p>
<p>nimittäni ca paçyämi</p>
<p>viparétäni keçava</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">na—nor; ca—also; çaknomi—am I able; avasthätum—to stay; bhramati—forgetting; iva—as; ca—and; me—my; manaù—mind; nimittäni—causes; ca—also; paçyämi—I see; viparétäni—just the opposite; keçava—O killer of the demon Keçé (Kåñëa).</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">I am now unable to stand here any longer. I am forgetting myself, and my mind is reeling. I see only causes of misfortune, O Kåñëa, killer of the Keçé demon.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Due to his impatience, Arjuna was unable to stay on the battlefield, and he was forgetting himself on account of this weakness of his mind. Excessive attachment for material things puts a man in such a bewildering condition of existence. Bhayaà dvitéyäbhiniveçataù syät (Bhäg. 11.2.37): such fearfulness and loss of mental equilibrium take place in persons who are too affected by material conditions. Arjuna envisioned only painful reverses in the battlefield—he would not be happy even by gaining victory over the foe. The words nimittäni viparétäni are significant. When a man sees only frustration in his expectations, he thinks, “Why am I here?” Everyone is interested in himself and his own welfare. No one is interested in the Supreme Self. Arjuna is showing ignorance of his real self-interest by Kåñëa’s will. One’s real self-interest lies in Viñëu, or Kåñëa. The conditioned soul forgets this, and therefore suffers material pains. Arjuna thought that his victory in the battle would only be a cause of lamentation for him.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.31</h3>
<h4>TEXT 31</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Na c é[eYaae_NauPaXYaaiMa hTva SvJaNaMaahve )</p>
<p>Na k-a¿e ivJaYa&#38; k*-Z&#60;a Na c raJYa&#38; Sau%aiNa c )) 31 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>na ca çreyo ’nupaçyämi</p>
<p>hatvä sva-janam ähave</p>
<p>na käìkñe vijayaà kåñëa</p>
<p>na ca räjyaà sukhäni ca</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">na—nor; ca—also; çreyaù—good; anupaçyämi—do I foresee; hatvä—by killing; sva-janam—own kinsmen; ähave—in the fight; na—nor; käìkñe—do I desire; vijayam—victory; kåñëa—O Kåñëa; na—nor; ca—also; räjyam—kingdom; sukhäni—happiness thereof; ca—also.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">I do not see how any good can come from killing my own kinsmen in this battle, nor can I, my dear Kåñëa, desire any subsequent victory, kingdom, or happiness.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Without knowing that one’s self-interest is in Viñëu (or Kåñëa), conditioned souls are attracted by bodily relationships, hoping to be happy in such situations. In such a blind conception of life, they forget even the causes of material happiness. Arjuna appears to have even forgotten the moral codes for a kñatriya. It is said that two kinds of men, namely the kñatriya who dies directly in front of the battlefield under Kåñëa’s personal orders and the person in the renounced order of life who is absolutely devoted to spiritual culture, are eligible to enter into the sun globe, which is so powerful and dazzling. Arjuna is reluctant even to kill his enemies, let alone his relatives. He thinks that by killing his kinsmen there would be no happiness in his life, and therefore he is not willing to fight, just as a person who does not feel hunger is not inclined to cook. He has now decided to go into the forest and live a secluded life in frustration. But as a kñatriya, he requires a kingdom for his subsistence, because the kñatriyas cannot engage themselves in any other occupation. But Arjuna has no kingdom. Arjuna’s sole opportunity for gaining a kingdom lies in fighting with his cousins and brothers and reclaiming the kingdom inherited from his father, which he does not like to do. Therefore he considers himself fit to go to the forest to live a secluded life of frustration.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.32, Bg 1.33, Bg 1.34, Bg 1.35, Bg 1.32-35</h3>
<h4>TEXTS 32–35</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>ik&#38;- Naae raJYaeNa GaaeivNd ik&#38;- &#62;aaeGaEJas„ivTaeNa va )</p>
<p>YaezaMaQaeR k-ax(i+aTa&#38; Naae raJYa&#38; &#62;aaeGaa&#34; Sau%aiNa c )) 32 ))</p>
<br />
<p>Ta wMae_viSQaTaa YauÖe Pa[a&#60;aa&#38;STYa¤-a DaNaaiNa c )</p>
<p>AacaYaaR&#34; iPaTar&#34; Pau}aaSTaQaEv c iPaTaaMaha&#34; )) 33 ))</p>
<br />
<p>MaaTaul&#47;a&#34; ìéura&#34; PaaE}aa&#34; XYaal&#47;a&#34; SaMbiNDaNaSTaQaa )</p>
<p>WTaaà hNTauiMaC^aiMa ganTaae_iPa MaDauSaUdNa )) 34 ))</p>
<br />
<p>AiPa }aEl&#47;aeKYaraJYaSYa heTaae&#34; ik&#38;- Nau Mahqk*-Tae )</p>
<p>iNahTYa DaaTaRraí&#92;aà&#34; k-a Pa[qiTa&#34; SYaaÂNaadRNa )) 35 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>kià no räjyena govinda</p>
<p>kià bhogair jévitena vä</p>
<p>yeñäm arthe käìkñitaà no</p>
<p>räjyaà bhogäù sukhäni ca</p>
<br />
<p>ta ime ’vasthitä yuddhe</p>
<p>präëäàs tyaktvä dhanäni ca</p>
<p>äcäryäù pitaraù puträs</p>
<p>tathaiva ca pitämahäù</p>
<br />
<p>mätuläù çvaçuräù pauträù</p>
<p>çyäläù sambandhinas tathä</p>
<p>etän na hantum icchämi</p>
<p>ghnato ’pi madhusüdana</p>
<br />
<p>api trailokya-räjyasya</p>
<p>hetoù kià nu mahé-kåte</p>
<p>nihatya dhärtaräñörän naù</p>
<p>kä prétiù syäj janärdana</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">kim—what use; naù—to us; räjyena—is the kingdom; govinda—O Kåñëa; kim—what; bhogaiù—enjoyment; jévitena—living; vä—either; yeñäm—of whom; arthe—for the sake; käìkñitam—is desired; naù—by us; räjyam—kingdom; bhogäù—material enjoyment; sukhäni—all happiness; ca—also; te—all of them; ime—these; avasthitäù—situated; yuddhe—on this battlefield; präëän—lives; tyaktvä—giving up; dhanäni—riches; ca—also; äcäryäù—teachers; pitaraù—fathers; puträù—sons; tathä—as well as; eva—certainly; ca—also; pitämahäù—grandfathers; mätuläù—maternal uncles; çvaçuräù—fathers-in-law; pauträù—grandsons; çyäläù—brothers-in-law; sambandhinaù—relatives; tathä—as well as; etän—all these; na—never; hantum—to kill; icchämi—do I wish; ghnataù—being killed; api—even; madhusüdana—O killer of the demon Madhu (Kåñëa); api—even if; trai-lokya—of the three worlds; räjyasya—for the kingdom; hetoù—in exchange; kim nu—what to speak of; mahé-kåte—for the sake of the earth; nihatya—by killing; dhärtaräñörän—the sons of Dhåtaräñöra; naù—our; kä—what; prétiù—pleasure; syät—will there be; janärdana—O maintainer of all living entities.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">O Govinda, of what avail to us are a kingdom, happiness or even life itself when all those for whom we may desire them are now arrayed on this battlefield? O Madhusüdana, when teachers, fathers, sons, grandfathers, maternal uncles, fathers-in-law, grandsons, brothers-in-law and other relatives are ready to give up their lives and properties and are standing before me, why should I wish to kill them, even though they might otherwise kill me? O maintainer of all living entities, I am not prepared to fight with them even in exchange for the three worlds, let alone this earth. What pleasure will we derive from killing the sons of Dhåtaräñöra?</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Arjuna has addressed Lord Kåñëa as Govinda because Kåñëa is the object of all pleasures for cows and the senses. By using this significant word, Arjuna indicates that Kåñëa should understand what will satisfy Arjuna’s senses. But Govinda is not meant for satisfying our senses. If we try to satisfy the senses of Govinda, however, then automatically our own senses are satisfied. Materially, everyone wants to satisfy his senses, and he wants God to be the order supplier for such satisfaction. The Lord will satisfy the senses of the living entities as much as they deserve, but not to the extent that they may covet. But when one takes the opposite way—namely, when one tries to satisfy the senses of Govinda without desiring to satisfy one’s own senses—then by the grace of Govinda all desires of the living entity are satisfied. Arjuna’s deep affection for community and family members is exhibited here partly due to his natural compassion for them. He is therefore not prepared to fight. Everyone wants to show his opulence to friends and relatives, but Arjuna fears that all his relatives and friends will be killed on the battlefield and he will be unable to share his opulence after victory. This is a typical calculation of material life. The transcendental life, however, is different. Since a devotee wants to satisfy the desires of the Lord, he can, Lord willing, accept all kinds of opulence for the service of the Lord, and if the Lord is not willing, he should not accept a farthing. Arjuna did not want to kill his relatives, and if there were any need to kill them, he desired that Kåñëa kill them personally. At this point he did not know that Kåñëa had already killed them before their coming into the battlefield and that he was only to become an instrument for Kåñëa. This fact is disclosed in following chapters. As a natural devotee of the Lord, Arjuna did not like to retaliate against his miscreant cousins and brothers, but it was the Lord’s plan that they should all be killed. The devotee of the Lord does not retaliate against the wrongdoer, but the Lord does not tolerate any mischief done to the devotee by the miscreants. The Lord can excuse a person on His own account, but He excuses no one who has done harm to His devotees. Therefore the Lord was determined to kill the miscreants, although Arjuna wanted to excuse them.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.36</h3>
<h4>TEXT 36</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>PaaPaMaevaé[YaedSMaaNhTvETaaNaaTaTaaiYaNa&#34; )</p>
<p>TaSMaaàahaR vYa&#38; hNTau&#38; DaaTaRraí&#92;aNSabaNDavaNa( )</p>
<p>SvJaNa&#38; ih k-Qa&#38; hTva Saui%Na&#34; SYaaMa MaaDav )) 36 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>päpam eväçrayed asmän</p>
<p>hatvaitän ätatäyinaù</p>
<p>tasmän närhä vayaà hantuà</p>
<p>dhärtaräñörän sa-bändhavän</p>
<p>sva-janaà hi kathaà hatvä</p>
<p>sukhinaù syäma mädhava</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">päpam—vices; eva—certainly; äçrayet—must come upon; asmän—us; hatvä—by killing; etän—all these; ätatäyinaù—aggressors; tasmät—therefore; na—never; arhäù—deserving; vayam—we; hantum—to kill; dhärtaräñörän—the sons of Dhåtaräñöra; sa-bändhavän—along with friends; sva-janam—kinsmen; hi—certainly; katham—how; hatvä—by killing; sukhinaù—happy; syäma—will we become; mädhava—O Kåñëa, husband of the goddess of fortune.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Sin will overcome us if we slay such aggressors. Therefore it is not proper for us to kill the sons of Dhåtaräñöra and our friends. What should we gain, O Kåñëa, husband of the goddess of fortune, and how could we be happy by killing our own kinsmen?</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">According to Vedic injunctions there are six kinds of aggressors: (1) a poison giver, (2) one who sets fire to the house, (3) one who attacks with deadly weapons, (4) one who plunders riches, (5) one who occupies another’s land, and (6) one who kidnaps a wife. Such aggressors are at once to be killed, and no sin is incurred by killing such aggressors. Such killing of aggressors is quite befitting any ordinary man, but Arjuna was not an ordinary person. He was saintly by character, and therefore he wanted to deal with them in saintliness. This kind of saintliness, however, is not for a kñatriya. Although a responsible man in the administration of a state is required to be saintly, he should not be cowardly. For example, Lord Räma was so saintly that people even now are anxious to live in the kingdom of Lord Räma (räma-räjya), but Lord Räma never showed any cowardice. Rävaëa was an aggressor against Räma because Rävaëa kidnapped Räma’s wife, Sétä, but Lord Räma gave him sufficient lessons, unparalleled in the history of the world. In Arjuna’s case, however, one should consider the special type of aggressors, namely his own grandfather, own teacher, friends, sons, grandsons, etc. Because of them, Arjuna thought that he should not take the severe steps necessary against ordinary aggressors. Besides that, saintly persons are advised to forgive. Such injunctions for saintly persons are more important than any political emergency. Arjuna considered that rather than kill his own kinsmen for political reasons, it would be better to forgive them on grounds of religion and saintly behavior. He did not, therefore, consider such killing profitable simply for the matter of temporary bodily happiness. After all, kingdoms and pleasures derived therefrom are not permanent, so why should he risk his life and eternal salvation by killing his own kinsmen? Arjuna’s addressing of Kåñëa as “Mädhava,” or the husband of the goddess of fortune, is also significant in this connection. He wanted to point out to Kåñëa that, as husband of the goddess of fortune, He should not induce Arjuna to take up a matter which would ultimately bring about misfortune. Kåñëa, however, never brings misfortune to anyone, to say nothing of His devotees.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.37, Bg 1.38, Bg 1.37-38</h3>
<h4>TEXTS 37–38</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>YaÛPYaeTae Na PaXYaiNTa l&#47;ae&#62;aaePahTaceTaSa&#34; )</p>
<p>ku-l&#47;+aYak*-Ta&#38; daez&#38; iMa}ad]aehe c PaaTak-Ma( )) 37 ))</p>
<br />
<p>k-Qa&#38; Na jeYaMaSMaai&#62;a&#34; PaaPaadSMaaiàviTaRTauMa( )</p>
<p>ku-l&#47;+aYak*-Ta&#38; daez&#38; Pa[PaXYaiÙJaRNaadRNa )) 38 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>yady apy ete na paçyanti</p>
<p>lobhopahata-cetasaù</p>
<p>kula-kñaya-kåtaà doñaà</p>
<p>mitra-drohe ca pätakam</p>
<br />
<p>kathaà na jïeyam asmäbhiù</p>
<p>päpäd asmän nivartitum</p>
<p>kula-kñaya-kåtaà doñaà</p>
<p>prapaçyadbhir janärdana</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">yadi—if; api—even; ete—they; na—do not; paçyanti—see; lobha—by greed; upahata—overpowered; cetasaù—their hearts; kula-kñaya—in killing the family; kåtam—done; doñam—fault; mitra-drohe—in quarreling with friends; ca—also; pätakam—sinful reactions; katham—why; na—should not; jïeyam—be known; asmäbhiù—by us; päpät—from sins; asmät—these; nivartitum—to cease; kula-kñaya—in the destruction of a dynasty; kåtam—done; doñam—crime; prapaçyadbhiù—by those who can see; janärdana—O Kåñëa.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">O Janärdana, although these men, their hearts overtaken by greed, see no fault in killing one’s family or quarreling with friends, why should we, who can see the crime in destroying a family, engage in these acts of sin?</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">A kñatriya is not supposed to refuse to battle or gamble when he is so invited by some rival party. Under such an obligation, Arjuna could not refuse to fight, because he had been challenged by the party of Duryodhana. In this connection, Arjuna considered that the other party might be blind to the effects of such a challenge. Arjuna, however, could see the evil consequences and could not accept the challenge. Obligation is actually binding when the effect is good, but when the effect is otherwise, then no one can be bound. Considering all these pros and cons, Arjuna decided not to fight.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.39</h3>
<h4>TEXT 39</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>ku-l&#47;+aYae Pa[&#60;aXYaiNTa ku-l&#47;DaMaaR&#34; SaNaaTaNaa&#34; )</p>
<p>DaMaeR Naíe ku-l&#38;&#47; k*-TòMaDaMaaeR_i&#62;a&#62;avTYauTa )) 39 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>kula-kñaye praëaçyanti</p>
<p>kula-dharmäù sanätanäù</p>
<p>dharme nañöe kulaà kåtsnam</p>
<p>adharmo ’bhibhavaty uta</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">kula-kñaye—in destroying the family; praëaçyanti—become vanquished; kula-dharmäù—the family traditions; sanätanäù—eternal; dharme—religion; nañöe—being destroyed; kulam—family; kåtsnam—whole; adharmaù—irreligion; abhibhavati—transforms; uta—it is said.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">With the destruction of dynasty, the eternal family tradition is vanquished, and thus the rest of the family becomes involved in irreligion.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">In the system of the varëäçrama institution there are many principles of religious traditions to help members of the family grow properly and attain spiritual values. The elder members are responsible for such purifying processes in the family, beginning from birth to death. But on the death of the elder members, such family traditions of purification may stop, and the remaining younger family members may develop irreligious habits and thereby lose their chance for spiritual salvation. Therefore, for no purpose should the elder members of the family be slain.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.40</h3>
<h4>TEXT 40</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>ADaMaaRi&#62;a&#62;avaTk*-Z&#60;a Pa[duZYaiNTa ku-l&#47;iñYa&#34; )</p>
<p>ñqzu duíaSau vaZ&#60;aeRYa JaaYaTae v&#60;aRSaªr&#34; )) 40 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>adharmäbhibhavät kåñëa</p>
<p>praduñyanti kula-striyaù</p>
<p>stréñu duñöäsu värñëeya</p>
<p>jäyate varëa-saìkaraù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">adharma—irreligion; abhibhavät—having become predominant; kåñëa—O Kåñëa; praduñyanti—become polluted; kula-striyaù—family ladies; stréñu—by the womanhood; duñöäsu—being so polluted; värñëeya—O descendant of Våñëi; jäyate—comes into being; varëa-saìkaraù—unwanted progeny.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">When irreligion is prominent in the family, O Kåñëa, the women of the family become polluted, and from the degradation of womanhood, O descendant of Våñëi, comes unwanted progeny.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Good population in human society is the basic principle for peace, prosperity and spiritual progress in life. The varëäçrama religion’s principles were so designed that the good population would prevail in society for the general spiritual progress of state and community. Such population depends on the chastity and faithfulness of its womanhood. As children are very prone to be misled, women are similarly very prone to degradation. Therefore, both children and women require protection by the elder members of the family. By being engaged in various religious practices, women will not be misled into adultery. According to Cäëakya Paëòita, women are generally not very intelligent and therefore not trustworthy. So the different family traditions of religious activities should always engage them, and thus their chastity and devotion will give birth to a good population eligible for participating in the varëäçrama system. On the failure of such varëäçrama-dharma, naturally the women become free to act and mix with men, and thus adultery is indulged in at the risk of unwanted population. Irresponsible men also provoke adultery in society, and thus unwanted children flood the human race at the risk of war and pestilence.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.41</h3>
<h4>TEXT 41</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Saªrae Nark-aYaEv ku-l&#47;ganaNaa&#38; ku-l&#47;SYa c )</p>
<p>PaTaiNTa iPaTarae ùeza&#38; lu&#47;áiPa&#60;@aedk-i§-Yaa&#34; )) 41 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>saìkaro narakäyaiva</p>
<p>kula-ghnänäà kulasya ca</p>
<p>patanti pitaro hy eñäà</p>
<p>lupta-piëòodaka-kriyäù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">saìkaraù—such unwanted children; narakäya—make for hellish life; eva—certainly; kula-ghnänäm—for those who are killers of the family; kulasya—for the family; ca—also; patanti—fall down; pitaraù—forefathers; hi—certainly; eñäm—of them; lupta—stopped; piëòa—of offerings of food; udaka—and water; kriyäù—performances.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">An increase of unwanted population certainly causes hellish life both for the family and for those who destroy the family tradition. The ancestors of such corrupt families fall down, because the performances for offering them food and water are entirely stopped.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">According to the rules and regulations of fruitive activities, there is a need to offer periodical food and water to the forefathers of the family. This offering is performed by worship of Viñëu, because eating the remnants of food offered to Viñëu can deliver one from all kinds of sinful actions. Sometimes the forefathers may be suffering from various types of sinful reactions, and sometimes some of them cannot even acquire a gross material body and are forced to remain in subtle bodies as ghosts. Thus, when remnants of prasädam food are offered to forefathers by descendants, the forefathers are released from ghostly or other kinds of miserable life. Such help rendered to forefathers is a family tradition, and those who are not in devotional life are required to perform such rituals. One who is engaged in the devotional life is not required to perform such actions. Simply by performing devotional service, one can deliver hundreds and thousands of forefathers from all kinds of misery. It is stated in the Bhägavatam (11.5.41) :</p>
<div class="quotes">
<p>devarñi-bhütäpta-nåëäà pitèëäà</p>
<p>na kiìkaro näyam åëé ca räjan</p>
<p>sarvätmanä yaù çaraëaà çaraëyaà</p>
<p>gato mukundaà parihåtya kartam</p></div>
<p>“Anyone who has taken shelter of the lotus feet of Mukunda, the giver of liberation, giving up all kinds of obligation, and has taken to the path in all seriousness, owes neither duties nor obligations to the demigods, sages, general living entities, family members, humankind or forefathers.” Such obligations are automatically fulfilled by performance of devotional service to the Supreme Personality of Godhead.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.42</h3>
<h4>TEXT 42</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>daezEreTaE&#34; ku-l&#47;ganaNaa&#38; v&#60;aRSaªrk-arkE-&#34; )</p>
<p>oTSaaÛNTae JaaiTaDaMaaR&#34; ku-l&#47;DaMaaRê XaaìTaa&#34; )) 42 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>doñair etaiù kula-ghnänäà</p>
<p>varëa-saìkara-kärakaiù</p>
<p>utsädyante jäti-dharmäù</p>
<p>kula-dharmäç ca çäçvatäù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">doñaiù—by such faults; etaiù—all these; kula-ghnänäm—of the destroyers of the family; varëa-saìkara—of unwanted children; kärakaiù—which are causes; utsädyante—are devastated; jäti-dharmäù—community projects; kula-dharmäù—family traditions; ca—also; çäçvatäù—eternal.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">By the evil deeds of those who destroy the family tradition and thus give rise to unwanted children, all kinds of community projects and family welfare activities are devastated.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Community projects for the four orders of human society, combined with family welfare activities, as they are set forth by the institution of sanätana-dharma, or varëäçrama-dharma, are designed to enable the human being to attain his ultimate salvation. Therefore, the breaking of the sanätana-dharma tradition by irresponsible leaders of society brings about chaos in that society, and consequently people forget the aim of life—Viñëu. Such leaders are called blind, and persons who follow such leaders are sure to be led into chaos.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.43</h3>
<h4>TEXT 43</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>oTSaàku-l&#47;DaMaaR&#60;aa&#38; MaNauZYaa&#60;aa&#38; JaNaadRNa )</p>
<p>Narke- iNaYaTa&#38; vaSaae &#62;avTaqTYaNauéué[uMa )) 43 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>utsanna-kula-dharmäëäà</p>
<p>manuñyäëäà janärdana</p>
<p>narake niyataà väso</p>
<p>bhavatéty anuçuçruma</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">utsanna—spoiled; kula-dharmäëäm—of those who have the family traditions; manuñyäëäm—of such men; janärdana—O Kåñëa; narake—in hell; niyatam—always; väsaù—residence; bhavati—it so becomes; iti—thus; anuçuçruma—I have heard by disciplic succession.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">O Kåñëa, maintainer of the people, I have heard by disciplic succession that those who destroy family traditions dwell always in hell.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Arjuna bases his argument not on his own personal experience, but on what he has heard from the authorities. That is the way of receiving real knowledge. One cannot reach the real point of factual knowledge without being helped by the right person who is already established in that knowledge. There is a system in the varëäçrama institution by which before death one has to undergo the process of atonement for his sinful activities. One who is always engaged in sinful activities must utilize the process of atonement called the präyaçcitta. Without doing so, one surely will be transferred to hellish planets to undergo miserable lives as the result of sinful activities.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.44</h3>
<h4>TEXT 44</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Ahae bTa MahTPaaPa&#38; k-Tau| VYaviSaTaa vYaMa( )</p>
<p>Yad]aJYaSau%l&#47;ae&#62;aeNa hNTau&#38; SvJaNaMauÛTaa&#34; )) 44 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>aho bata mahat päpaà</p>
<p>kartuà vyavasitä vayam</p>
<p>yad räjya-sukha-lobhena</p>
<p>hantuà sva-janam udyatäù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">aho—alas; bata—how strange it is; mahat—great; päpam—sins; kartum—to perform; vyavasitäù—have decided; vayam—we; yat—because; räjya-sukha-lobhena—driven by greed for royal happiness; hantum—to kill; sva-janam—kinsmen; udyatäù—trying.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Alas, how strange it is that we are preparing to commit greatly sinful acts. Driven by the desire to enjoy royal happiness, we are intent on killing our own kinsmen.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">Driven by selfish motives, one may be inclined to such sinful acts as the killing of one’s own brother, father or mother. There are many such instances in the history of the world. But Arjuna, being a saintly devotee of the Lord, is always conscious of moral principles and therefore takes care to avoid such activities.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.45</h3>
<h4>TEXT 45</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>Yaid MaaMaPa[Taqk-arMaXañ&#38; XañPaa&#60;aYa&#34; )</p>
<p>DaaTaRraí&#92;a r&#60;ae hNYauSTaNMae +aeMaTar&#38; &#62;aveTa( )) 45 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>yadi mäm apratékäram</p>
<p>açastraà çastra-päëayaù</p>
<p>dhärtaräñörä raëe hanyus</p>
<p>tan me kñemataraà bhavet</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">yadi—even if; mäm—me; apratékäram—without being resistant; açastram—without being fully equipped; çastra-päëayaù—those with weapons in hand; dhärtaräñöräù—the sons of Dhåtaräñöra; raëe—on the battlefield; hanyuù—may kill; tat—that; me—for me; kñema-taram—better; bhavet—would be.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Better for me if the sons of Dhåtaräñöra, weapons in hand, were to kill me unarmed and unresisting on the battlefield.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">It is the custom—according to kñatriya fighting principles—that an unarmed and unwilling foe should not be attacked. Arjuna, however, decided that even if attacked by the enemy in such an awkward position, he would not fight. He did not consider how much the other party was bent upon fighting. All these symptoms are due to soft-heartedness resulting from his being a great devotee of the Lord.</p>
<h3>Bg 1.46</h3>
<h4>TEXT 46</h4>
<div class="deva">
<p>SaÅYa ovac</p>
<p>WvMau¤-aJauRNa&#34; Sa&#38;:Yae rQaaePaSQa oPaaivXaTa( )</p>
<p>ivSa*JYa SaXar&#38; caPa&#38; Xaaek-Sa&#38;ivGanMaaNaSa&#34; )) 46 ))</p>
</div>
<div class="roman">
<p>saïjaya uväca</p>
<p>evam uktvärjunaù saìkhye</p>
<p>rathopastha upäviçat</p>
<p>visåjya sa-çaraà cäpaà</p>
<p>çoka-saàvigna-mänasaù</p>
</div>
<p class="synonyms">SYNONYMS</p>
<p class="transliteration">saïjayaù uväca—Saïjaya said; evam—thus; uktvä—saying; arjunaù—Arjuna; saìkhye—in the battlefield; ratha—of the chariot; upasthe—on the seat; upäviçat—sat down again; visåjya—putting aside; sa-çaram—along with arrows; cäpam—the bow; çoka—by lamentation; saàvigna—distressed; mänasaù—within the mind.</p>
<p class="translation-head">TRANSLATION</p>
<p class="translation-text">Saïjaya said: Arjuna, having thus spoken on the battlefield, cast aside his bow and arrows and sat down on the chariot, his mind overwhelmed with grief.</p>
<p class="purport-head">PURPORT</p>
<p class="purport-text">While observing the situation of his enemy, Arjuna stood up on the chariot, but he was so afflicted with lamentation that he sat down again, setting aside his bow and arrows. Such a kind and soft-hearted person, in the devotional service of the Lord, is fit to receive self-knowledge.</p>
<p>Thus end the Bhaktivedanta Purports to the First Chapter of the Çrémad Bhagavad-gétä in the matter of Observing the Armies on the Battlefield of Kurukñetra.</p>
   </body>
</html>